Guide to the Frederick S. Parker Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frederick Sheldon Parker papers
1845-1916
MS 1026
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
The papers consist entirely of Frederick S. Parker's research notes about Napoleon I in 24 volumes, a catalogue of his library, and manuscript copies of two works on Napoleon by French authors.
Parker, Frederick Sheldon, 1852-1916
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Frederick S. Parker, 1916.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of materials about Napoleon I compiled by Frederick S. Parker. They consist of twenty-four bound volumes of research notes entitled "Napoleonana," as well as subject and author indices to the notes, and a catalogue of Parker's library. Also included among these papers are manuscript copies of two works on Napoleon by French authors.
These papers were apparently given to Yale University by the estate of Frederick Parker in 1916.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick Sheldon Parker was born July 26, 1852, in New Haven, Conn., where his ancestor, Edward Parker, an English Puritan, settled in 1644, soon after the founding of the colony. His father, Frederick Sheldon Parker, was a paper manufacturer of that city, and the son of Dr. Joseph Parker, a physician of Litchfield, Conn., who served as a surgeon in the Revolutionary Army, and Lydia (Harrison) Parker. His mother was Martha, daughter of William and Frances (Longyear) Newton of Albany, N. Y., and a descendant of Thomas Newton, who settled in Fairfield, Conn., in 1639, and of Gov. William Bradford of Plymouth Colony.
He was fitted for Yale at Hopkins Grammar School, and for two years of his college course was a member of his Class Glee Club. He received First Colloquy appointments, and served on the Senior Promenade and Class Supper committees.
After graduating he remained at Yale for a year to take a post-graduate course in history, at the conclusion of which he entered the Columbia Law School, where he received his LL.B. in 1876. From November, 1875, until 1878 he was in the office of Blatchford, Seward, Griswold & DaCosta of New York City, being for a year their managing clerk. In 1878 he entered the office of the United States district attorney in that city, where he remained for two years, during part of which he served as an assistant district attorney. In 1880 he formed a partnership with Alfred Taylor (B.S. Lewisburg 1866, LL.B. Columbia 1871). On the death of Mr. Taylor in 1894 the name of the firm was changed from Taylor & Parker to Parker & Aaron, Mr. Herman Aaron (B.S. College of the City of New York 1881, LL.B. Columbia 1883), who had also been in the former firm, becoming Mr. Parker's junior partner. Mr. Parker continued in the active practice of his profession, giving his attention principally to corporation law, until his death, which occurred in Brooklyn, N. Y., September 9, 1916, from oedema of the lungs, following an operation for appendicitis. Interment was in Greenwood Cemetery, Brooklyn.
Throughout his life, one of Mr. Parker's chief interests was in collecting Napoleona. He made many trips to Europe, during which he gathered much material, and his collection eventually came to be considered one of the largest and best in the country. This he bequeathed in his will to Yale University. He wrote and edited much on the subject of Napoleona, and had become a recognized authority. He was a member of the Society of Mayflower Descendants, the Society of Colonial Wars, the Sons of the Revolution, and the Society of Founders and Patriots. For many years he served as a vestryman of Grace Church, Brooklyn. He was Secretary of the Class of 1873 for three years after graduation.
On May 16, 1876, he was married in Brooklyn to Josephine Mason, daughter of John J. and Mary M. Hill. Her death occurred Febraury 18, 1879. They had one son, Frederick Sheldon, Jr., who died at birth, February 6, 1879. Mr. Parker leaves his brother, William Newton Parker, a graduate of the College in 1879. His brother-in-law, Simeon Baldwin Chittenden, received his B.A. from Yale in 1865, and the latter's son, Simeon B. Chittenden, Jr., is a graduate of the College in 1902. Another nephew, John Hill Morgan, graduated from the College in 1893 and from the School of Law in 1896.
(Taken from Yale College Obituary Record, 1915-20, pp. 343-344).
Historians; Napoleon, Emperor of the French, I, 1769-1821; Parker, Frederick Sheldon, 1852-1916
- Inventory
  - Parker, Frederick S.: "Napoleonana"
    - Volumes of research notes
      - 1-4, 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 4)
      - 5-8, [1893-1895?] (Box 2, Folder 5 - 8)
      - 9-12, 1895-1897 (Box 3, Folder 9 - 12)
      - 13-16, 1897-1902 (Box 4, Folder 13 - 16)
      - 17-20, 1902-1905 (Box 5, Folder 17 - 20)
      - 21-22, 1912, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 21 - 22)
      - 23-24 (blank), undated (Box 6, Folder 23 - 24)
    - Notecards
      - Author index, undated (Box 7)
      - Subject index, undated (Box 8)
  - Perrot, A. M.: "Itineraire general de Napoleon" (Ms copy), 1845 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Proudhon, Pierre Joseph: "Napoleon the first" (Ms translation), undated (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Catalogue of the library of Frederick S. Parker (notecards), undated (Box 10–11)